Guide to the Leonard Bacon Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Leonard Bacon papers
1834-1962
1897-1962
YCAL MSS 487
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
37
(92 boxes) + 1 framed art object
The collection consists of correspondence, writings, printed material and other papers that document the life and work of the poet Leonard Bacon. Correspondence is both professional and personal, and documents Bacon's writing and publishing activities as well as his personal and family relationships. Writings include drafts and proofs for many of his published works including Ulug Beg (1923), Lost Buffalo, and Other Poems (1930), The Furioso (1932), Dream and Action (1934), and Semi-Centennial (1939), as well as works translated by Bacon, such as Luis de Camões's The Lusiads (1950). Printed material includes several boxes of printed versions of Bacon's poetry and other writings, as well as pamphlets, reprints, newspaper clippings, and ephemera collected by Bacon. Other papers include three scrapbooks documenting Bacon's career from 1923 to 1946, as well as a small quantity of personal documents and photographs.
Bacon, Leonard, 1887-1954
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Leonard and Martha Bacon, 1955-1968. Gift of Helen H. Bacon, 1996. Other material acquired from various sources, 1967-1979. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Leonard Bacon (1887-1954)
Leonard Bacon, American poet, literary critic, and teacher, was born in Solvay, New York on May 26, 1887. He was the son of Nathaniel Terry Bacon and Helen Hazard Bacon. He graduated in 1909 from Yale, where he studied with Chauncey Brewster Tinker and co-edited the literary magazine. Bacon taught English at the University of California, Berkeley between 1910 and 1923. Shortly after the successful publication of his first book Ulug Beg (1923), he retired from education to pursue his literary career. Bacon published several volumes of poetry, including Sunderland Capture, and Other Poems (1940) which won the Pulitzer Prize for poetry, as well as translations and an autobiography. In addition to his books, Bacon's poems were published in magazines such as The Saturday Review of Literature, The Atlantic, and The New Yorker.
Bacon married Martha Sherman Stringham on May 16, 1912, and they had three daughters. Bacon died in 1954.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, writings, printed material and other papers that document the life and work of the poet Leonard Bacon. Correspondence is both professional and personal, and documents Bacon's writing and publishing activities as well as his personal and family relationships. Writings include drafts and proofs for many of his published works including Ulug Beg (1923), Lost Buffalo, and Other Poems (1930), The Furioso (1932), Dream and Action (1934), and Semi-Centennial (1939), as well as works translated by Bacon, such as Luis de Camões's The Lusiads (1950). Printed material includes several boxes of printed versions of Bacon's poetry and other writings, as well as pamphlets, reprints, newspaper clippings, and ephemera collected by Bacon. Other papers include three scrapbooks documenting Bacon's career from 1923 to 1946, as well as a small quantity of personal documents and photographs.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Correspondence, 1834-1962. II. Writings, 1906-1954. III. Printed Material, undated. IV. Other Papers, 1917-1951.
American literature -- 20th Century; American poetry -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Photographs; Poets; Bacon, Leonard, 1887-1954
- Correspondence, 1834-1962; Series I; 16.48; (41 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I consists of the personal and professional correspondence of Leonard Bacon. While correspondence is chiefly incoming, some files include original and retained copies of outgoing letters. Also included in this series is third-party family correspondence, chiefly between Leonard Bacon's parents, Nathaniel Terry Bacon and Helen Hazard Bacon, and a file containing a letter by Reverend Leonard Bacon.
  - "A" General, 1939-1953; 2 (Box 1)
  - Academy of American Poets, 1947-1953; 3 (Box 1)
  - Aldington, Richard, 1931-1954; 7 (Box 1)
  - Allen, Hervey, 1929-1947 (Box 1)
  - American Academy, 1947-1953 (Box 1)
  - Amphlett, 1926-1947 (Box 1)
  - Angell, James Rowland, 1933-1947 (Box 2)
  - Archer, William, 1946-1948 (Box 2)
  - Arnold, Grace Angell, 1946 (Box 2)
  - Arrowsmith, 1905-1954 (Box 2)
  - Atlantic Monthly, 1934-1953 (Box 2)
  - Atomic Scientists, 1947-1949; 2 (Box 2)
  - "B" General, 1911-1954; 3 (Box 2)
  - Bacon, Alice, 1926-1952 (Box 3)
  - Bacon, Helen Hazard, 1897-1910; 9 (Box 3)
    Letters to Leonard Bacon
  - Bacon, Helen Hazard, 1911-1925; 9 (Box 4)
  - Bacon, Josephine Dascom, 1931-1955 (Box 4)
  - Bacon, Leonard, Rev., 1834-1839 (Box 4)
  - Bacon, Leonard, 1911-1924; 13 (Box 5)
    Letters to his wife Martha Bacon
  - Bacon, Leonard, 1925-1929; 8 (Box 6)
  - Bacon, Leonard, 1937-1952; 14 (Box 7)
  - Bacon, Leonard, 1898-1917; 8 (Box 8)
    Letters to his mother Helen Hazard Bacon
  - Bacon, Leonard, 1918-1924; 5 (Box 9)
  - Bacon, Leonard, 1935-1947; 24 (Box 10)
    Letters to his daughter Helen H. Bacon
  - Bacon, Leonard, 1948-1953; 23 (Box 11)
  - Bacon, Leonard, 1939-1950 (Box 12)
    Letters to his daughter Martha Ballinger
  - Bacon, Leonard, 1941-1950 (Box 12)
    Letters to his daughter Alice Westlake
  - Bacon, Leonard, 1910-1924; 2 (Box 12)
    Letters to his father Nathaniel T. Bacon
  - Bacon, Martha, 1924-1954; 2 (Box 13)
  - Bacon, Martha, 1917-1949; 5 (Box 13)
    Letters to her husband Leonard Bacon
  - Bacon Martha, 1918-1950; 5 (Box 14)
  - Bacon, Martha, 1913-1923; 2 (Box 15)
    Letters to her mother-in-law Helen Hazard Bacon
  - Bacon, Martha, 1925-1931 (Box 15)
    Letters to A.C. Day.
  - Bacon, Martha, 1927 September 29 (Box 15)
  - Bacon, Nathaniel T., 1909 (Box 15)
    Letters to his wife Helen Hazard Bacon
  - Bacon, Nathaniel T., 1919-1925; 4 (Box 15)
    Letters to his son Leonard Bacon
  - Bacon, Nathaniel T., 1872-1923; 4 (Box 16)
  - Bates, Katharine Lee, 1908-1928 (Box 17)
  - Baumann, Carol, 1946-1953; 2 (Box 17)
  - Baynes, Cary, 1949-1950 (Box 17)
  - Beers, Henry A., 1912-1949 (Box 17)
  - Benét, Frances, 1912-1939 (Box 17)
  - Benét, Laura, 1937-1950 (Box 17)
  - Benét, Lawrence V., 1947 (Box 17)
  - Benét, Rosemary, 1939-1952 (Box 17)
  - Benét, William Rose, 1937-1950 (Box 17)
  - Biddle, Alfred, 1934-1952 (Box 17)
  - Biddle, Alice, 1946-1954 (Box 17)
  - Biddle, Constance, 1934-1947; 2 (Box 17)
  - Biddle, Constance, 1948-1959 (Box 18)
  - Biddle, George, 1931-1948 (Box 18)
  - Biddle family, 1940-1945 (Box 18)
  - Blaisdell, Nathaniel, 1925-1954; 3 (Box 18)
  - Blake, Robert T., 1926-1948 (Box 18)
  - Blodget, F. Malbone, 1945-1948 (Box 18)
  - Bollingen Foundation, 1949-1950 (Box 18)
  - Borie, Mrs. Beauvaux, undated (Box 18)
  - Boston Museum of Fine Arts, 1926 (Box 18)
  - Boxer, C. R., 1948-1949 (Box 18)
  - Boynton, Horace, 1952-1953 (Box 18)
  - Bradford, Gamaliel, 1921-1951; 2 (Box 18)
  - Braithwaite, William Stanley, 1923-1928 (Box 18)
  - Brewer, George, 1908-1953 (Box 19)
  - Brewster, W. T. (William Tenney), 1924-1960; 2 (Box 19)
  - Brock, Irving, 1946-1948 (Box 19)
  - Brook, Van Wyck, 1932-1948 (Box 19)
  - Brooke, Tucker, 1936-1944 (Box 19)
  - Brown University, 1940-1951 (Box 19)
  - Bryn Mawr, 1939-1947 (Box 19)
  - Bucht, Gösta, 1907-1910 (Box 19)
  - Bundy, Harvey H., 1939-1947 (Box 19)
  - Burgess, Dorothy, 1948-1952 (Box 19)
  - Burlingame, Roger, 1939-1953 (Box 19)
  - "C" General, 1910-1954 (Box 19)
  - Calhoun College, Yale, 1933-1949 (Box 20)
  - Calkins, Deborah D., 1936-1949 (Box 20)
  - Campbell, Roy, undated (Box 20)
  - Canby, Henry S., 1923-1952; 2 (Box 20)
  - Canfield, Cass, 1927-1951; 2 (Box 20)
  - Carson, Rachel L., 1951 (Box 20)
  - Carver, George Washington to Miss Hazard, 1927 December 16 (Box 20)
  - Castle, Linda, 1939-1948 (Box 20)
  - Cates, Dudley, 1926-1942 (Box 20)
  - Century Association, 1927-1949 (Box 20)
  - Chafee, Zach, 1917-1954 (Box 20)
  - Colamussi, Fabrisio, 1948-1950 (Box 20)
  - Colby, Charles W., 1946-1948 (Box 20)
  - Colt, Henry F., 1933-1952 (Box 20)
  - Congress, Library of, 1946-1951 (Box 21)
  - Corwin, Margaret Bacon, 1927-1950 (Box 21)
  - Corwin, Margaret Trumbull, 1914-1954 (Box 21)
  - Coward-McCann Inc., 1937-1953 (Box 21)
  - Cronin, Grover J., 1942-1950 (Box 21)
  - Crowell, Thomas Y., Co., 1943-1950 (Box 21)
  - "D" General, 1924-1954 (Box 21)
  - Damon, S. Foster, 1946-1947 (Box 21)
  - Davidson, Gustav, 1951 (Box 21)
  - Davis, Elmer, 1936-1952 (Box 21)
  - Day, Carol, 1952-1953 (Box 21)
  - Day, George P., 1946-1950 (Box 21)
  - Day family, 1915-1942 (Box 21)
  - De Banke, Cecile, 1944 (Box 22)
  - De Forest, Elizabeth, 1949-1951 (Box 22)
  - De la Mare, Walter, 1943-1951 (Box 22)
  - Delano, William Adams, 1946-1952 (Box 22)
  - Diman, Louise, 1912-1951 (Box 22)
  - Dunes Club, 1937-1948 (Box 22)
  - Durham, Henriette & Bull, 1932-1950 (Box 22)
  - Durst, W. H., 1933-1954 (Box 22)
  - Dutton Inc., 1937-1950; 2 (Box 22)
  - Duval, 1939-1953 (Box 22)
  - Dwight, H. D., 1947-1953 (Box 22)
  - "E" General, 1946-1955; 2 (Box 22)
  - Edgerton, Franklin, 1947-1951 (Box 22)
  - Edwards, Hubert L., 1946-1954 (Box 22)
  - Einstein, Albert, 1946-1959 (Box 22)
  - Emory, Kenneth, 1939-1940 (Box 22)
  - "F" General, 1926-1954; 3 (Box 23)
  - Fackenthal, Frank D., 1936-1939 (Box 23)
  - Farrar & Rinehart, 1933-1952; 2 (Box 23)
  - Faust, Dorothy, 1938-1954; 2 (Box 23)
  - Faust, Frederick, 1921-1954 (Box 23)
  - Fisher, Irving N., 1934-1951 (Box 23)
  - Forbes, W. Cameron, 1946-1951 (Box 23)
  - Frost, Robert, 1939-1951 (Box 23)
  - Furniss, Edward, 1941-1949 (Box 23)
  - "G" General, 1905-1953; 3 (Box 23)
  - Gallatin, Albert, 1939-1946 (Box 23)
  - Gilder, Rodman, 1946-1953 (Box 23)
  - Goddard, Peggy, 1946-1950 (Box 23)
  - Goodrich, Chauncey S., Jr., 1925-1935 (Box 23)
  - Gourevitch, Gregoire, 1946-1951 (Box 23)
  - Greene, Henry Copley, 1938-1950 (Box 24)
  - Greenslet, Ferris, Houghton Mifflin, 1928-1947 (Box 24)
  - Gugler, Eric, 1939-1953 (Box 24)
  - "H" General, 1914-1954; 3 (Box 24)
  - Ham, Roswell G., 1933-1949 (Box 24)
  - Hanke, Lewis, 1947-1951 (Box 24)
  - Harcourt, Brace, 1940-1944 (Box 24)
  - Harper & Brothers, 1924-1949 (Box 24)
  - Harper's Magazine, 1910-1951 (Box 24)
  - Hart, Walter Morris, 1946-1954 (Box 24)
  - Harvard University, 1921-1948 (Box 24)
  - Hazard, Caroline, 1920-1932 (Box 25)
  - Hazard, Dora, 1921-1934 (Box 25)
  - Hazard, J. P., 1931 (Box 25)
  - Hazard, M. P. B., 1929-1935 (Box 25)
  - Hazard, R., 1926-1948 (Box 25)
  - Hazard, Thomas Pierrepont, 1947-1952 (Box 25)
  - Hazard Family, 1928-1954; 2 (Box 25)
  - Hillyer, Robert, 1929-1949 (Box 25)
  - Hinckley, Allen, Tillinghast & Wheeler, 1926-1946 (Box 25)
  - Hispanic Institute in Florida, 1950-1951 (Box 25)
  - Hispanic Society, 1950-1953 (Box 25)
  - Hodgson, Ralph, 1947-1952 (Box 25)
  - Hoffmann, Irene, 1949-1954 (Box 25)
  - Holmes, John, 1947-1953 (Box 25)
  - Howard, Sidney, 1924-1946; 2 (Box 25)
  - Howe, M. A. De Wolfe, 1944-1955 (Box 25)
  - Hunt, Dorothy, 1929-1952 (Box 26)
  - Huntington, Archer M., 1948-1953 (Box 26)
  - Hutchins, Robert M., 1952-1953 (Box 26)
  - "J" General, 1923-1951; 2 (Box 26)
  - James, William & Alice, 1939-1953 (Box 26)
  - Jung, C. G. (Carl Gustav), 1924-1949; 3 (Box 26)
  - "K" General, 1930-1952; 2 (Box 26)
  - Keats-Shelley Association of America, 1948-1951 (Box 26)
  - Keith, Elmer D., 1912-1954 (Box 26)
  - Keith, Joseph Joel, 1949-1953 (Box 26)
  - Keith, Susan and Elmer, 1912-1933 (Box 26)
  - Keith, Susan, 1904-1954; 4 (Box 27)
  - Keith, Susan, 1908-1952 (Box 27)
    Letter to her mother
  - Knapp, Martin and Sally, 1946-1951 (Box 28)
  - Knopf, Alfred A., 1923-1950 (Box 28)
  - Knox, Mildred, 1947-1950 (Box 28)
  - "L" General, 1933-1954 (Box 28)
  - Lachman, Arthur, 1952-1953; 2 (Box 28)
  - Landon, Harold M. and Frederica, 1946-1951; 3 (Box 28)
  - Laurens, Dorothy, 1931-1954 (Box 28)
  - Lawson, Andrew C., 1943 August 24, undated (Box 29)
  - Lay, Charles Downing, 1946-1952 (Box 29)
  - Lay, Norma, 1951-1952 (Box 29)
  - LeClercq, Jacques, 1923-1951 (Box 29)
  - Lemmon, Robert S., 1948-1950 (Box 29)
  - Leonard, Dorothy, 1951-1954 (Box 29)
  - Lewis, Sinclair, undated (Box 29)
  - Lewis, Wilmarth S., 1927-1953; 2 (Box 29)
  - Livermore, Harold and Ann, 1948-1954 (Box 29)
  - Lohmann, Carl A., 1947-1951 (Box 29)
  - Lombardi, Maurice E., 1928-1952 (Box 29)
  - Loveman, Amy, 1933-1954 (Box 29)
  - "M" General, 1921-1953; 2 (Box 29)
  - McCord, David, 1948-1953 (Box 29)
  - McGinley, Phyllis, 1951-1953 (Box 29)
  - McHarry, Charles P., 1949-1950 (Box 30)
  - McMahon, Frank H., 1948 (Box 30)
  - MacVeagh, Lincoln, 1924 (Box 30)
  - Manwaring, Elizabeth W., 1941-1945 (Box 30)
  - Margulies, Irwin, 1946-1951 (Box 30)
  - Masefield, John, undated (Box 30)
  - Mayer, Lloyd, 1942-1953 (Box 30)
  - Mendell, C. W., 1948-1949 (Box 30)
  - Merrick, Vaughan, 1934-1952 (Box 30)
  - Michaelson, L. W., 1950-1952 (Box 30)
  - Midkiff, Frank E., 1939-1946 (Box 30)
  - Moe, Henry Allen, 1946-1947 (Box 30)
  - Moffitt, James K., 1947-1950 (Box 30)
  - Moore, Douglas, 1946-1952 (Box 30)
  - Moore, Robert Thomas, 1949-1953 (Box 30)
  - Morgan, E. M., 1946-1947 (Box 30)
  - Morison, Samuel Eliot, 1915-1950 (Box 30)
  - Morley, Frank V., 1946-1949 (Box 30)
  - Murphy, Robert C., 1946-1951 (Box 30)
  - "N" General, 1939-1951 (Box 30)
  - National Institute of Arts and Letters, 1941-1952 (Box 30)
  - New York Public Library, 1941-1953 (Box 30)
  - Newcomb, M. J., 1933-1952 (Box 30)
  - Newton, B. C., 1946-1954 (Box 30)
  - Northrop, F. S. C., 1947-1949 (Box 31)
  - Noyes, Alfred, 1948-1951 (Box 31)
  - Noyes, George R., 1913-1957; 3 (Box 31)
  - "O" General, 1909-1962 (Box 31)
  - Oliver-Smith, Philip, 1938-1947 (Box 31)
  - Oxford University Press, 1933-1950; 3 (Box 31)
  - "P" General, 1927-1953; 2 (Box 31)
  - Page, Curtis Hidden, 1930-1931 (Box 31)
  - Parr, Charles McKew, 1950-1953 (Box 31)
  - Parsons, Geoffrey, 1935-1946 (Box 31)
  - Pearson, Norman Holmes, 1952-1954 (Box 32)
  - Perry, Lewis, 1940-1952 (Box 32)
  - Petersson, Ruth, 1935-1948 (Box 32)
  - Potter, George R., 1950-1951 (Box 32)
  - Powel, Harford, 1945-1953 (Box 32)
  - Prime-Stevenson, E. I., 1907-1927 (Box 32)
  - Providence Journal, 1926-1949 (Box 32)
  - Pucelli, Rodolfo, 1936-1953 (Box 32)
  - "Q" General, 1948 (Box 32)
  - "R" General, 1911-1954; 2 (Box 32)
  - Ray, M. H., 1919-1949 (Box 32)
  - Ray, Mary, 1948-1950 (Box 32)
  - Redman, Mercedes L., 1952-1962, undated; 2 (Box 33)
  - Reynal & Hitchcock, 1943-1946 (Box 33)
  - Ripley, Mabel B., 1927-1950 (Box 33)
  - Roberts, Arthur, 1912-1949; 2 (Box 33)
  - Rogers, Francis, 1947-1948 (Box 33)
  - Rose, Selden, 1940-1953; 2 (Box 33)
  - Rushmore, Arthur, 1927-1953; 5 (Box 33)
  - Ryder, Arthur W., 1929, undated (Box 34)
  - "S" General, 1910-1954 (Box 34)
  - S. John, 1950-1953 (Box 34)
  - St. George's School, 1899-1954; 4 (Box 34)
  - Saturday Review of Literature, 1927-1952; 2 (Box 34)
  - Saturday Review of Literature, 1927-1952; 3 (Box 35)
  - Schevill, Margaret, 1937-1951 (Box 35)
  - Schoolcraft, John L., 1947-1954 (Box 35)
  - Scudder, Stevens & Clark, 1950-1952 (Box 35)
  - Sergeant, Elizabeth S., 1949-1950 (Box 35)
  - Shepard, Arthur, 1946-1954 (Box 35)
  - Sherman, French & Co., 1914-1915 (Box 35)
  - Smith, Henry Clapp, 1948-1953 (Box 35)
  - Smith, Ralph C., 1942-1948 (Box 35)
  - Smith, Warren H., 1939-1953 (Box 35)
  - Stevens, George Lippincott, J.B. Lippincott Co., 1939-1950 (Box 35)
  - Stewart, George, 1947-1954 (Box 35)
  - Stilman, Mrs., 1930 December 16 (Box 35)
  - Stokes, Harold Phelps, 1948-1954 (Box 35)
  - Stringham, Roland, 1922-1954; 3 (Box 35)
  - Sturges, Benjamin R., 1948-1954 (Box 36)
  - Sturges, Chaffee & Hazard, 1930-1953; 2 (Box 36)
  - Sturges, Rush, 1926-1949; 2 (Box 36)
  - Sullivan, Nancy, undated (Box 36)
  - Swiggett, Howard, 1947-1949 (Box 36)
  - "T" General, 1925-1952 (Box 37)
  - Taggard, Genevieve, 1930-1946 (Box 37)
  - Tavern Club, 1934-1954 (Box 37)
  - Thacher, Tom, 1917-1954 (Box 37)
  - Thomas, A. E. and Ethel, 1946-1947 (Box 37)
  - Thompson, Bea, 1952-1953 (Box 37)
  - Thompson, Lawrance, 1947 (Box 37)
  - Thompson, Sir George and family, 1940-1953; 2 (Box 37)
  - Tierney, Agnes L., 1943-1946 (Box 37)
  - Tillinghast Browning, Dorothy, 1939-1951; 4 (Box 37)
  - Tinker, Chauncey Brewster, 1910-1952; 3 (Box 37)
  - Troxell, Gilbert, 1946-1947; 2 (Box 37)
  - "U" General, 1930-1950 (Box 38)
  - Untermeyer, Louis, 1943-1946 (Box 38)
  - "V" General, 1909-1950 (Box 38)
  - Vernon, Ambrose White, 1946-1948 (Box 38)
  - Vinal, Harold, 1935-1946 (Box 38)
  - Vollmer, Major Arthur, 1940-1943 (Box 38)
  - "W" General, 1910-1954; 2 (Box 38)
  - Walden, Howard T., 1946-1947 (Box 38)
  - Wallner, Louis, 1934-1950 (Box 38)
  - Warner, Sylvia T., 1951-1953; 3 (Box 38)
  - Wellesley College, 1933-1948 (Box 38)
  - Westlake, John, 1947-1952 (Box 38)
  - White, Lawrence Grant, 1947-1948 (Box 38)
  - Whitney, Elizabeth, 1947-1950 (Box 38)
  - Whitney, Peter, 1946-1953 (Box 38)
  - Wilder, Thornton, 1946-1949 (Box 38)
  - Williams, Stanley T., 1927-1953 (Box 38)
  - Williams, W.H., 1921-1949 (Box 38)
  - Williams, W.W., 1918-1948 (Box 38)
  - Wister, Marina, 1938-1943 (Box 39)
  - Wister, Owen, 1913-1938 (Box 39)
    Letters to Helen Hazard Bacon
  - Wolff, Toni, 1926-1950 (Box 39)
  - Wood, John D., 1949-1952 (Box 39)
  - Wood, Stanley, 1926-1927 (Box 39)
  - Woolsey, T. S. and R., 1931-1948 (Box 39)
  - Woolsey, Dorothy, 1930-1952 (Box 39)
  - Wright, John K., 1942-1948 (Box 39)
  - Wright, Orville, 1919-1920 (Box 39)
  - Wright, Sylvia, 1939-1954 (Box 39)
  - Wrogh, Lawrence C., 1943-1952 (Box 39)
  - "Y" general, 1946-1950 (Box 39)
  - Yale Literary Magazine, 1938-1951 (Box 39)
  - Yale Review, 1940-1953 (Box 39)
  - Yale University Library, 1921-1952; 3 (Box 39)
  - Yale University Press, 1918-1952 (Box 39)
  - "Z" general, 1947 (Box 40)
  - Zabriskie, George, 1940-1953; 4 (Box 40)
  - "Zurich", 1925-1934 (Box 40)
  - Unsorted correspondence, 1926-1954; 2 (Box 40)
  - Unsorted correspondence, undated; 9 (Box 41)
- Writings, 1906-1954; Series II; 17.18; (41 boxes)
  Series II includes drafts and proofs of many of Bacon's published works, including Ulug Beg (1923), Lost Buffalo, and Other Poems (1930), The Furioso (1932), Dream and Action (1934), and Semi-Centennial (1939), as well as works translated by Bacon, such as Luis de Camões's The Lusiads (1950). Also included is one box of memoranda, correspondence, and notes and drafts related to Bacon's work on a military dictionary and lexicography project. Writings also include drafts of poems, essays, book reviews, journals, and translations by Bacon, both published and unpublished.
  Arranged alphabetically by title or in some case by author. Untitled materials are arranged by genre.
  - "Agamemnon", undated (Box 42)
    Autograph, 21 leaves
    Translation
  - "Analytical Psychology and Poetry", undated (Box 42)
    Autograph, 13 leaves
    Essay typescript, carbon, 8 leaves
  - Animula Vagula, 1926 (Box 42)
    Autograph drafts
  - "Autumn as a Language", circa 1954; 2 (Box 42)
    Typescript original, 22 leaves
    Autograph and typescript
  - Baldur and Loki, undated; 5 (Box 42)
    Typescript original, 76 leaves
    Typescript carbon, 76 leaves
    Typescript original, with manuscript corrections, 70 leaves
    Typescript carbon, 70 leaves
    Autograph, 76 leaves
  - "Ballad of Ammunition Jones", undated (Box 43)
    Autograph, 7 leaves
    Typescript original, 8 leaves
  - "Ballad of Ariel", undated (Box 43)
    Typescript original, 4 leaves
  - "The Ballad of Buccleugh", 1906 (Box 43)
    Autograph, 1 notebook
  - "The Ballad of the Laird of Keith", 1906 (Box 43)
  - Ballads of the Serbs with George R. Noyes, undated; 4 (Box 43)
    Typescript original, 167 leaves
    Typescript original, revised, 167 leaves
    Typescript carbon, 167 leaves
    Typed drafts, with some correspondence, 1 folder
  - "Banquet of the Poets", undated (Box 44)
    Typescript original, 17 leaves
  - "Billy Phelps Pundit Poem", undated (Box 44)
    Carbon, 2 leaves, 3 copies
  - "Black Brothers", undated; 3 (Box 44)
    Typescript original, 100 leaves, story
    Autograph, 149 leaves
    Typescript carbon, with manuscript corrections, 100 leaves
  - "Briareus," photostatic copy, undated (Box 81)
  - "A Brief History of the 13th Century", undated (Box 44)
    Autograph, 11 leaves
  - Bullinger Bound, undated; 2 (Box 44)
    Autograph & typescript
    Typescript, corrected
  - "By the Rivers of Babylon", undated; 3 (Box 44)
  - "Camões and the Glory of Portugal", undated; 7 (Box 45)
  - "Camões Readers", undated (Box 45)
  - "Camões' Reading", undated (Box 45)
  - Camões, notes for translation, index cards, undated (Box 93)
  - "Carducci", undated (Box 45)
    Autograph & typescript, translations
  - "The Centaur", undated (Box 45)
    Typescript original, 7 leaves
  - Charlemagne notes, undated (Box 45)
  - "Commemorative Tribute to Leonard Bacon," by Chauncey Brewster Tinker, undated (Box 45)
    Typescript carbon
  - Cornelius, Helen. In Tract of Time: Introduction, 1935-1936 (Box 45)
    Typescript carbon, 3 leaves, with correspondence
  - "Count Ward", undated; 4 (Box 45)
    Typescript original, 40 leaves
    Autograph, 80 leaves
    Autograph, 54 leaves
    Typescript original, 27 leaves
  - D'Annunzio, Gabriele. The Ship, undated; 2 (Box 46)
    Autograph, 153 leaves, translation
    Autograph, 208 leaves
  - Day of Fire, 1943 (Box 46)
    Typescript and carbon, corrected
  - "Delia Bacon", 1937 (Box 46)
  - "Disharmonies", undated (Box 46)
    Autograph, 26 leaves
    Typescript carbon, 4 leaves, 2 copies
  - Dream and Action, undated; 3 (Box 46)
    Autograph, 65 leaves
    Autograph, 68 leaves
    Setting typescript original, 68 leaves
    Plate proof, 13 leaves
  - "Dream Ballad of Demios the Greek", undated (Box 46)
    Typescript original, 2 leaves
  - European Twilight and Other Poems, undated (Box 47)
  - "The Exploration of Cocaigne", undated (Box 47)
  - The Furioso, undated; 3 (Box 47)
    Manuscript draft, bound
    Setting typescript original, 220 leaves, with some autograph.
  - "Gamaliel Bradford", undated; 2 (Box 47)
    Typescript carbon, 161 leaves
    Typescript original & carbon
  - The Goose on the Capitol, undated (Box 48)
    Setting typescript original, 71 leaves
  - Guinea-fowl, 1927 (Box 48)
    Galley proof
  - "Heinie Bergman's Saga", undated (Box 48)
    Autograph pencil, 9 leaves
    Autograph ink, 8 leaves
    Typescript carbon, 89 leaves
  - "John Dryden", undated (Box 48)
    Autograph, 9 leaves
  - "John Keats", undated (Box 48)
    Autograph, typescript original & carbon
  - The Lay of the Cid, undated (Box 48)
  - Legend of Quincibald, undated; 2 (Box 48)
    Autograph
  - Legend of Quincibald, undated (Box 49)
  - Light and Power, undated; 4 (Box 49)
    Autograph, 111 leaves
    Typescript carbon, 113 leaves, with manuscript corrections
    Typescript original, 113 leaves, with manuscript corrections
    Autograph, 100 leaves
  - "Lines Read at the Annual Dinner of the Colonial Society of New England", 1936 November 21 (Box 49)
    Autograph, 5 leaves
    Typescript carbon, 5 leaves
  - Lost Buffalo, undated; 3 (Box 49)
    Autograph, 93 leaves
    Typescript original, 62 leaves
    Setting typescript original, 127 leaves
  - The Lusiads, by Luis de Camões. Translation., undated; 10 (Box 50)
    Autograph, typescript original and carbon
  - The Lusiads, by Luis de Camões. Translation., undated; 6 (Box 51)